<resources>
    <string name="app_name">UK Castles</string>

    <!--Titles for Details Activity-->
    <string name="opening_times_title">Opening times change due to time of year - click to see current opening times</string>
    <string name="operated_by_title">Operated by: </string>
    <string name="status_details_title">Current status:</string>
    <string name="address_title">See location on a map</string>
    <string name="history_title">Brief history of the site</string>
    <string name="audio_title">Detailed history of the site</string>
    <string name="details_rating_title">Site rating</string>
    <string name="click_website_string">. Click to visit their website.</string>
    <string name="music_title_text">Some medieval music to get you in the mood for your visit</string>
    <string name="share_long_click_title">Share</string>
    <string name="full_image_long_click_title">See full image slideshow</string>

    <!--Shared preference strings-->
    <string name="shared_preference_distance_key">distance_preference</string>
    <string name="shared_preference_sort_key">sort_preference</string>
    <string name="shared_preference_filter_key">filter_preference</string>
    <string name="shared_preference_distance_default">Miles</string>
    <string name="shared_preference_sort_default">A-Z</string>
    <string name="shared_preference_filter_default">None</string>

    <!--Strings for text in bottom toolbar about whether device online or offline-->
    <string name="offline_string">Offline</string>
    <string name="online_string">Online</string>

    <!--Strings for Notifications-->
    <string name="notification_channel_description">Channel to receive weekly notifications about castles</string>
    <string name="notification_channel_name">My notification channel</string>
    <string name="notification_title">Castle App</string>
    <string name="notification_content">We now have 24 castles to view</string>

    <!--Strings for Widgets-->
    <string name="appwidget_text">UK Castles</string>
    <string name="add_widget">Add widget</string>
    <string name="share_intent_title">Share using</string>
    <string name="castle_app_widget_image">Castle image for widget</string>

    <!--Strings for Adapter-->
    <string name="km_away_string">KMs away</string>
    <string name="miles_away_string">Miles away</string>

    <!--Strings for MainActivity-->
    <string name="no_location_permission_message">Please enable location permissions to use this app</string>
    <string name="close_app_alert_option">Close App</string>
    <string name="toolbar_subtitle_text">Click Castle to see more info</string>
    <string name="permission_rationale_title">Permission needed</string>
    <string name="permission_rationale_message">This permission is needed for the app to run</string>
    <string name="cancel_alert_button">Cancel</string>
    <string name="ok_alert_button">OK</string>
    <string name="search_text_view_hint">Enter search</string>
    <string name="search_button_text">Search</string>
    <string name="reset_button_text">Reset</string>

    <!--Strings for SettingsActivity-->
    <string name="settings_toolbar_title">Settings</string>
    <string name="content_description_image_item">Image of Castle</string>

    <!--Strings for FullImageActivity-->
    <string name="full_image_content_description">Full image in full image activity</string>

    <!--Strings for Settings Fragment-->
    <string name="settings_distance_title">Distance</string>
    <string name="settings_sort_title">Sort by</string>
    <string name="settings_filter_title">Filter by</string>

    <!--Settings strings-->
    <string-array name="distance_array">
        <item>Km</item>
        <item>Miles</item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="sort_array">
        <item>A-Z</item>
        <item>Distance</item>
        <item>Rating</item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="filter_array">
        <item>None</item>
        <item>English Heritage</item>
    </string-array>

    <!--History strings-->
    <string-array name="wark_history">
        <item>Built in the mid-twelfth centuryBuilt in the mid-twelfth century</item>
        <item>In 1327, the castle twice held out against Scottish sieges</item>
        <item>The powerful and influential Percy family was given the castle by the crown in the early 14th century</item>
        <item>The Percy family helped Henry IV win the throne from Richard II. But the family later rebelled against the new king. The rebellion was defeated at the battle of Shewsbury.</item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="dunstan_history">
        <item>Built by the Earl Thomas of Lancaster in the early 14th century</item>
        <item>Earl Thomas led an unsuccessful rebellion against King Edward II, causing him to be executed by the king. As a result, the castle was seized by the crown.</item>
        <item>John of Gaunt, who founded the royal House of Lancaster which later took part in the Wars of the Roses, greatly expanded the castle in the late 14th century.</item>
        <item>The castle was traded back and forth during the Wars of the Roses, which represented its strategic importance in the north of England. The damage sustained during these wars was never fully repaired. </item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="rising_history">
        <item>Built during the mid 12th century by an Anglo-Norman lord</item>
        <item>The castle was famously the home of Queen Isabella after the accession of her son, Edward III, to power.</item>
        <item>Queen Isabella joined forces with Roger Mortimer to rebel and bring down her husband Edward II. She ruled along with Mortimer for a short period before her son, Edward III, seized control of the nation.</item>
        <item>The castle quickly became valued for its hunting facilities rather than its strategic importance.</item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="berk_history">
        <item>Built on a key route between London and the Midlands by the Normans in the 11th century</item>
        <item>Thomas Becket was granted the castle in the 12th century, before falling out with the King and being stripped of the castle.</item>
        <item>The castle was besieged by the French Prince Louis in 1216. He was attempting to take control of the crown after the death of King John.</item>
        <item>The castle was taken apart for stone as early as the mid 16th century, and is now a sparse ruin.</item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="warwick_history">
        <item>The castle was originally a wooden fort construction by William I</item>
        <item>The Beauchamp family controlled the castle for much of the medieval period and were influential on the course of English history.</item>
        <item>The castle passed to Richard Neville after the Beauchamp line ended. He was known as the kingmaker for he often held the balance of power during the Wars of the Roses, and was therefore able to gather much power to himself.</item>
        <item>The castle was used as a military base up until the early 17th century, when it was converted into a country house.</item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="bamburgh_history">
        <item>The site was formally a stronghold of Celtic Britons and Anglo-Saxons.</item>
        <item>The fort was destroyed by the Vikings only around 70 years before the arrival of the Normans in England.</item>
        <item>The Normans later constructed a new castle on this site, which has evolved into what can be seen today. </item>
        <item>The castle was the first in England to be defeated by artillery during a siege in the Wars of the Roses. </item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="alnwick_history">
        <item>Alnwick Castle was first built by Norman lords following William the Conqueror’s invasion of England.</item>
        <item>The castle was sieged many times by the Scottish throughout the 12th century, with David I of Scotland successfully capturing it in 1136.</item>
        <item>The powerful and influential Percy family took control of the castle in the 13th century, who turned the castle into a major fortress in the England-Scotland border region.</item>
        <item>The castle was used as a stand-in for Hogwarts during the Harry Potter films</item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="dover_history">
        <item>This version of Dover castle was built in the 11th century.</item>
        <item>However, due to its strategic importance, fortifications on this site likely pre-date the Roman invasions.</item>
        <item>The castle was rebuilt significantly during the Napoleonic wars, and was occupied by British forces to defeat against a potential French Calais-Dover invasion.</item>
        <item>Dover castle was a military command centre during the second world war. The evacuation of Dunkirk was directed from this site.</item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="raby_history">
        <item>Built by the Neville family in the late 14th century</item>
        <item>Cecily Neville was born In the castle, her children included King Edward IV and Richard III, the Yorkist kings of England.</item>
        <item>The Neville family attempted to support the claim of the catholic Mary, Queen of Scots, to the English throne. Following this, the castle was taken into royal ownership.</item>
        <item>The castle is still lived in today.</item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="caen_history">
        <item>The first stone building was built by Edward I of England following his attempts to control Wales.</item>
        <item>The castle was sacked in 1294 during a Welsh rebellion against English rule.</item>
        <item>With the accession of the Tudor family to the crown in 1485 and due to their Welsh heritage, relations between Wales and England improved so the castle was no longer an important military base.</item>
        <item>Despite its poor condition, the royalist controlled castle was sieged several times during the English civil wars.</item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="carlisle_history">
        <item>This castle was built in Norman times and sits close to the ruins of Hadrian’s wall.</item>
        <item>During Roman times, a fort was built on this same site.</item>
        <item>The castle was captured by David, King of Scotland, in the early 12th century. Due to its strategic location on the Anglo-Scottish border it was sieged many times in the middle ages.</item>
        <item>The castle was the site of a bloody siege during the Wars of the Roses, with the Lancastrians teaming up with the Scots to seize the castle from the Yorkists.</item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="conway_history">
        <item>Built by Edward I in the late 13th century, it was one of many castles built in the North of Wales during this time.</item>
        <item>It repelled many welsh sieges, including in 1294 when Madog ap Llywelyn failed to take the castle.</item>
        <item>Richard II took refuge at the castle in 1399, as his power slipped away following defeat by the future King Henry IV. </item>
        <item>The castle was dismantled significantly following the English civil wars as Parliament did not want it used in further revolts.</item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="bodiam_history">
        <item>Built by one of Edward III’s knights in the late 14th century, it is unusual in that is has no keep.</item>
        <item>It was originally constructed to provide protection against the French during the 100 years war.</item>
        <item>The castle’s owner was a supporter of the House of Lancaster during the Wars of the Roses. However, it was taken by Yorkist forces during the wars and only returned to its owner when Henry VII took the crown, effectively ending the Wars of the Roses.</item>
        <item>The castle was dismantled in the 17th century, but in the 19th century began a gradual restoration to its current state.</item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="rochester_history">
        <item>This castle was founded just after the Norman conquest of Britain.</item>
        <item>The castle was sieged by King John in 1215. He managed to bring down a corner of the keep and was later able to starve the defenders into surrender.</item>
        <item>Following repair, the castle was again sieged in 1264 by Simon de Montfort, who was rebelling against the king. Their siege was unsuccessful as royal reinforcements forced off the attackers. However, the castle surrendered when the rebels crushed the king’s forces on the battlefield.</item>
        <item>The castle never fully recovered from these two sieges, and gradually fell into a state of disrepair. </item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="stirling_history">
        <item>The castle is built on a large volcanic rock above the river Forth, and is on a very strategically important site.</item>
        <item>Stirling castle was the site of much fighting during the Wars of Scottish independence, involving characters such as William Wallace, Robert the Bruce, Edward I and Edward II.</item>
        <item>During these wars the battles of Stirling Bridge and Bannockburn took place. These were two of the greatest victories for the Scottish over the English.</item>
        <item>James II infamously murdered Earl Douglas at Stirling castle.  </item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="edin_history">
        <item>Built on a commanding rock, this site has been an important strategic location since at least Roman times.</item>
        <item>This castle is the most besieged castle in Britain, due to its important strategic location and the constant fighting between the English and Scottish throughout the middle ages.</item>
        <item>The castle formerly housed the Scottish royal treasury as it was seen as the safest place in the country to hold such valuable artifacts.</item>
        <item>Bonnie Price Charlie was the last person to try and take the castle. He was unsuccessful, eventually giving up and marching into England to press his claim to the throne. </item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="durham_history">
        <item>The castle was first built in 1072 by William the Conqueror.</item>
        <item>The castle was besieged during one of the many northern rebellions against Norman rule in 1080. </item>
        <item>The castle was put into the hands of Prince-Bishop’s for much of its early medieval history. The role of these bishops was to act as a buffer between England and Scotland. </item>
        <item>The Bishop of Durham still maintains offices at the castle.</item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="conis_history">
        <item>The estates of Conisbrough were in the hands of King Harold prior to his defeat by the Norman king William the Conqueror.</item>
        <item>The Normans originally built a wooden castle here, but it was upgraded to stone in the late 12th century by Hamelin Plantagenet, the illegitamte half-brother of King Henry II.</item>
        <item>Thomas, Early of Lancaster, controlled the castle in 1322 when he rebelled against King Edward II. He was defeated and executed, and the castle was seized personally by King Edward.</item>
        <item>During the Wars of the Roses, the castle was the personal property of Richard of York, and later of his son King Edward Iv. </item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="lancaster_history">
        <item>The castle is part of the Duchy of Lancaster, which is owned by the Monarch of the UK.</item>
        <item>The caslte was damaged by Scottish invasions in 1322 and 1389.</item>
        <item>The parliamentarians captured the castle early in the English Civil War. In response, the king sent an army to retake the city of Lancaster, including the castle. They were unsuccessful and the castle and city remained under parliament control.</item>

    </string-array>

    <string-array name="york_history">
        <item>Clifford\'s tower was originally a wooden castle built on the orders of William the Conqueror.</item>
        <item>In 1069, the castle was captured an partially destroyed by an anglo-saxon and viking alliance rebelling against William I. The events at York led to the "Harrowing of the North" by William.</item>
        <item>The castle was upgraded to stone in the middle of the 13th century by Henry III.</item>
        <item>The caslte was an important military base during the Anglo-Scottish wars from 1298 to 1338.</item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="cardiff_history">
        <item>The original Motte and Bailey castle was built on this site shortly after the Norman invasion of England.</item>
        <item>The castle was rebuilt in stone in the 12th century.</item>
        <item>The welsh prince Owain Glyndwr took the castle in 1404 during his rebellion against English control of Wales.</item>

    </string-array>

    <string-array name="pontefract_history">
        <item>The castle was originally constructed by the Normans shortly after their conquest of England.</item>
        <item>Thomas, Earl of Lancaster, was executed outside of the walls of the castle following his failed rebellion against King Edward II. Edward was dining in the great hall as the execution was carried out.</item>
        <item>The castle was part of the house of Lancaster, and was seized by Richard II when he banished Henry Bolingbroke. Henry later returned, overthrew Richard and became Henry IV.</item>
        <item>Richard II was held at the castle, and was likely starved to death whilst at the castle.</item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="prudhoe_history">
        <item>Built in the late eleventh century to defend against Scottish incursions into England.</item>
        <item>The castle was sieged many times during Anglo-Scottish wars in the early middle ages. However, it was never taken by the Scottish, the only castle in Northumberland with that honour. </item>
        <item>In 1381 the castle was purchased by the powerful Percy family, who descended from William de Percy, who was a Norman supporter of William the Conqueror. </item>
        <item>In 1403-1405 the Percy family rebelled against King Henry IV, and so the castle was taken by the king and granted to his brother, the Duke of Lancaster. However, the Percy family were restored to their ownership of the castle by Henry VII in 1470.</item>

    </string-array>

    <string-array name="richmond_history">
        <item>The original castle was constructed on this site by the Norman invaders after the harrying of the north, when William I divided the north Yorkshire lands among his loyal followers.</item>
        <item>Henry II seized the castle in 1158 and completed the keep which can still be seen today.</item>
        <item>The castle’s ownership frequently changed hands as the castle was owned by the Dukes of Brittany in France. Often when tensions with the French flared up, the castle confiscated by the English crown.</item>
        <item>In 1372, ownership of the castle was fully passed to the English crown.</item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="lewes_history">
        <item>Originally built after the Norman invasion to dominate the port of Lewes, which was an important port in Saxon England.</item>
        <item>The battle of Lewes took part nearby, where the rebel Simon de Montfort defeated the royalist forces, and became de facto ruler of England.</item>
        <item>The crown invested significantly in the castle in the early 14th century to protect against raids from the French, who England was currently fighting the 100 years’ war against. </item>
        <item> During the Peasants’ Revolt in the late 14th century, the castle was attacked by rioters and looted.</item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="oxford_history">
        <item>Built shortly after the Norman invasion, the first stone fortifications were built as early as 1073.</item>
        <item>During the war of succession between King Stephen and the Empress Matilda, Matilda was surrounded by Stephen’s forces at the castle. However, she escaped by being lowered over the castle walls and creeping away through the snow whilst wearing a white nightdress.</item>
        <item>During the Baron’s revolt against King John in 1216, the castle was besieged successfully by John.  </item>
        <item>The castle was largely destroyed by the parliamentarians after the English civil war, as they did with many of the countries castles which they saw as Royalist symbols.</item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="maiden_history">
        <item>Maiden castle is an Iron Age hill fort. It was expanded around 450 BC to become the largest hill fort in Britain.</item>
        <item>A hill fort is essentially a fortified hill-top settlement, using earth works to secure the settlement.</item>
        <item>Maiden caslte, unusually for hill forts, was still occupied during the Roman conquest of Britain in AD 43. After the Roman conquest, the site was abandoned.</item>
        <item>In the late 4th century a religious structure was built on the hill, most likely worshipping a combination of Roman and British gods.</item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="tamworth_history">
        <item>Tamworth was an important Anglo-saxon town in the kingdom of Mercia, and was the chief residence of King Offa of Mercia, who was an extremely powerful Anglo-Saxon king in the 8th century.</item>
        <item>Successive Viking attacks destroyed much of the town, and it only recovered after the Norman conquest when the Norman steward Robert Despenser built a Norman motte and bailey castle on the site of the old Anglo-Saxon defences. </item>
        <item>The Marmion family, also supporters of the Norman royal family, ruled the castle after Robert died and left the castle to his niece. This family controlled the castle until 1294 and they were responsible for turning it into the stone building seen today, although many additions were made to the castle in later years.</item>
        <item>The castle was garrisoned by Royalists during the English Civil War, but was captured by Parliament in 1643 and held by them for the rest of the war.</item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="lincoln_history">
        <item>Lincoln sits on high ground overlooking a generally flat landscape, this strategic importance was recognised by the Romans who built a legionary fortress on this site.</item>
        <item>A major Norman castle was then constructed on this site following the invasion of William the Conqueror.</item>
        <item>During the war for the crown between Stephen and Matilda, Lincoln Castle was besieged by Stephen. He was then attacked by a force loyal to Matilda, and was defeated and imprisoned, allowing Matilda to rule England for around 18 months.</item>
        <item>Following the signing of Magna Carta, Lincoln Castle was the site of another battle between Henry III and the future Louis VIII of France, who had earlier been invited over to England to fight against King John. Henry III decisively won the battle and it was a turning point in the war against Louis and the English barons who supported him.</item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="colchester_history">
        <item>Colchester Castle was built by the Normans after the invasion of William the Conqueror.</item>
        <item>Colchester was a major Roman centre, and the large size of the keep is due to the use of the masonry base of the Roman Temple of Claudius, which was the largest Roman temple in Britain.</item>
        <item>King John besieged Colchester Castle during his war with the Barons, who garrisoned the castle with French troops sent over by Prince Louis of France. John successfully took the castle via negotiations with the defenders.</item>
        <item>The castle was later used as a prison. In the mid-17th century, the Witchfinder General, Matthew Hopkins, used the castle to interrogate and imprison suspected witches.</item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="restormel_history">
        <item>Built in the South West of England, the castle was originally built by the Normans to try and control the area, which was a centre for Anglo-Saxon resistance following the Norman invasion in 1066.</item>
        <item>Simon de Montfort seized the castle without a fight in 1264 as he took power from Henry III. Henry’s supporters took the castle back the next year.</item>
        <item>The castle passed into the ownership of the crown in 1299, but was not extensively lived in.</item>
        <item>The castle was in a state of disrepair from as early as the mid 14th century. </item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="ludlow_history">
        <item>Founded after the Norman conquest, Ludlow Castle was one of the first stone castles in England.</item>
        <item>The castle was heavily involved in the war for the English crown between Stephen and Matilda. Stephen took the castle in 1139 and granted it to one of his knights. However, this knight later lost the castle to the de Lacy family during an inter-family conflict.</item>
        <item>Prince Edward (the future Edward I) gathered his supporters at the castle in 1265, and was able to defeat Simon de Montfort and gain back power for his father Henry III. Simon had previously rebelled against the king and taken power for himself.</item>
        <item>The castle was an important seat of power for the Yorkists during the Wars of the Roses, as the castle was inherited by the Duke of York in 1425.</item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="berkeley_history">
        <item>The fast castle was built here almost immediately after the Norman invasion in 1066.</item>
        <item>Henry II granted a royal charter to the owner of the castle in 1153 to allow the owner to rebuild a more extensive castle on the site. </item>
        <item>The deposed Edward II was held at Berkeley castle in 1327. During his time captive at the castle, his supporters attacked the castle and rescued him. This rescue was short-lived and he was returned to the castle shortly afterwards and he was likely murdered at the castle.</item>
        <item>During the Civil War, Parliament captured the castle with the use of cannon. The castle was not allowed to be repaired following the civil war, as parliament saw castles as symbol of royal dominance of the country.</item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="belvoir_history">
        <item>Originally a Norman castle existed on this site, Belvoir was originally a royal manor until it was granted to Robert de Ros in 1257.</item>
        <item>The Norman castle was ruined by the 15th century, and a new castle was built on the site by 1555. The castle was a Royalist stronghold during the English Civil War, even housing the King for a night during the war.</item>
        <item>After the Civil War, parliament destroyed the castle and a stately home was built in its place by 1668.</item>
        <item>The castle was rebuilt in the early 19th century by the Duke and Duchess of Rutland in the gothic revival style.</item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="longtown_history">
        <item>Longtown was originally home to a Roman fort, the ditch of which was deepened and widened to protect against welsh incursion into England in 1055.</item>
        <item>A small Norman castle was built close to the site of the current castle shortly after the Norman conquest of England.</item>
        <item>The castle was upgraded to stone in the 12th century, and that is the structure we see today. </item>
        <item>The castle had fallen into disrepair by the early 15th century. However, Henry IV refortified the castle in 1403 in response to the Welsh uprising by Owain Glyndwr.</item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="harlech_history">
        <item>Harlech Castle was built by Edward I during his invasion of Wales in the late 13th century.</item>
        <item>Owain Glyndwr, the last Welsh Prince of Wales, took the castle in 1404 and made it his headquarters for the rest of the uprising. However, by 1409 Owain was recaptured and Wales was back under the control of England.</item>
        <item>The castle was held by the Lancastrians for much of the the Wars of the Roses, before it was captured by the Yorkists in 1468. It was the last major fortification held by the Lancastrians at that point and had been the launch-pad for many Lancastrian revolts against the Yorkist King Edward IV.</item>
        <item>The damage done in the siege of 1468 was only repaired during the English Civil War, when the royalists repaired the castle. The castle was the last major royalist stronghold to surrender to parliament.</item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="lindisfarne_history">
        <item>The castle was built in 1550 mainly using stones from the Priory which was shut down and plundered by Henry VIII following the break with the Catholic church.</item>
        <item>The union of England and Scotland reduced the importance of Lindisfarne castle, although it maintained a garrison.</item>
        <item>In the civil war, Parliament captured the castle from the Royalists, and with it took control of the port on the island.</item>
        <item>The castle was briefly captured by the Jacobites in 1715, before they were forced to run away on news of an approaching English force from Berwick.</item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="launceston_history">
        <item>Built just after the Norman invasion, this castle was the administrative centre of the earldom of Cornwall.</item>
        <item>The castle was rebuilt in stone in the late-12th century.</item>
        <item>The earldom of Cornwall, and the castle, passed to Henry III’s younger brother Richard in 1227. He reworked the castles defences using money from the Cornish tin mining industry.</item>
        <item>The castle was briefing owned by Piers Gaveston, the controversial favourite of Edward II. However, by the time the castle passed into the hands of the son of Edward III, it was reported as being in poor condition.</item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="totnes_history">
        <item>Totnes was the site of a fortified burh in Devon during the Saxon times. Its strategic importance lead to it being raided many times by the Vikings.</item>
        <item>Totnes castle was originally constructed by the Normans shortly after their invasion, likely following the rebellion against King William in the South West shortly after he took the English crown.</item>
        <item>King John seized the castle from its legal owner during his reign and granted it to one of his supporters. After John’s death, however, it passed back to the legal owner.</item>
        <item>The castle was significantly rebuilt in the early 14th century, however the castle fell into disrepair by the end of the Wars of the Roses.</item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="wallingford_history">
        <item>Built shortly after the Norman invasion, this castle was one of the most powerful royal castles in the 12th and 13th centuries.</item>
        <item>The castle was held by supporters of Matilda during her war for the crown with Stephen. It was sieged many times, but never taken.</item>
        <item>The castle was owned by King John during his reign, and he used it throughout his wars with the Barons.</item>
        <item>Simon de Montfort captured the castle in 1264 and briefly used it to hold the royal family prisoner.</item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="kenilworth_history">
        <item>The castle was founded in the early 12th century by the then treasurer to Henry I.</item>
        <item>Due to its strategic importance, Henry II took the castle into royal possession during a revolt against him by his son.</item>
        <item>King John spent a lot of resources upgrading Kenilworth Castle after he was excommunicated. John had to cede he castle as part of his signing Magna Carta, and it only returned to royal possession during the reign of his son Henry III.</item>
        <item>The castle is ruined because of the slighting of the castle following the English Civil War.</item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="middleham_history">
        <item>A motte and bailey castle was originally built in Middleham shortly after the Norman invasion of England.</item>
        <item>The stone castle was likely built on the current site in the late 12th century.</item>
        <item>The castle came into the hands of the Neville family in 1270, and eventually into the hands of Richard Neville, the Earl or Warwick, who was known as the kingmaker during the Wars of the Roses.</item>
        <item>The future Richard III married Anne Neville and took the castle as his main home following the death of the Earl of Warwick. During his reign, Richard rarely if ever visited the castle.</item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="beeston_history">
        <item>The castle was built in the early 1220’s for the Earl of Chester. The castle is unusual as it does not have a keep, instead using natural features of the land to make the bailey’s themselves strongholds.</item>
        <item>King Henry III inherited the Earldom of Cheshire and increased the size of the castle during his wars with the Welsh, where the castle was used to hold prisoners of war.</item>
        <item>Henry gave the castle and the Earldom of Cheshire to his heir, and ever since it has been given to the heir to the throne.</item>
        <item>The castle was in ruin at the start of the English Civil War, however, parliament repaired it and garrisoned it. The castle was lost to a tiny royal force, who crept into the castle at night. The parliamentarian castle governor was shot for his failure to hold the castle.</item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="pendennis_history">
        <item>Pendennis castle was built by Henry VIII as part of his fort building programme to protect against potential French invasion.</item>
        <item>In the late 16th century, the keep and gun platform was expanded in response to a growing threat from catholic Spain.</item>
        <item>The castle was taken by Parliament in 1646, during the English civil war, after a successful siege. The castle was a formidable fortress, and briefly housed Prince Charles during the war.</item>
        <item>The castle saw service during both world wars, and was upgraded in response to the renewed French threat following the French revolution and rise of Napoleon. </item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="portchester_history">
        <item>Due to its strategic importance, a Roman fort was constructed on the site of the castle in the late 3rd century.</item>
        <item>The fort was used by the Saxon’s to defend about Viking raids on the southern coast. Edward the Elder, son of Alfred the Great, took control of the castle for this purpose in 904.</item>
        <item>The Normans built a later castle on this site, and it was a royal castle for a long period from 1154. It was besieged and taken by the French in 1216, but later was returned to English control.</item>
        <item>Edward III gathered his army for his invasion of France in 1346. This army famously went onto to win a decisive victory at the Battle of Crecy.</item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="dunnottar_history">
        <item>The Scottish King Donald II was killed at Dunnottar during a Viking raid in 900. The castle was destroyed in the raid.</item>
        <item>The castle was captured from an English garrison by William Wallace in 1297. Wallace burned the church where the English were hiding and destroyed the castle.</item>
        <item>Mary, Queen of Scots visited the castle several times, including with her young son, the future James I of England.</item>
        <item>Oliver Cromwell sieged the castle in 1651 during his campaign in Scotland after the English civil war. The castle held out for 8 months before surrendering upon the arrival of heavy cannons at the siege. </item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="kenmure_history">
        <item>The semi-independent Lords of Galloway possibly had a fortress on this site prior to the 13th century.</item>
        <item>The core of the current castle was constructed in the 17th century by the Gordon family, who were made Viscounts of Kenmure by Charles I.</item>
        <item>The 6th Viscount of Kenmure was executed for his role in the Jacobite rising of 1715. His estates, including the castle, were forfeit and the castle was in ruin by 1790.</item>
        <item>The Gordon’s were granted the viscount status back in 1824, and the castle was modernised considerably during the 19th century.</item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="spynie_history">
        <item>This castle was the fortified seat of the Bishops of Moray for 500 years and was founded in the late 12th century.</item>
        <item>The site was used by administrators for King Edward I during his occupation of Scotland in the late 13th century.</item>
        <item>The castle was owned by the Scottish King Robert III allowing him to grant the castle to Bishop William of Moray.</item>
        <item>The bishops continued to develop and modernise the castle, with the largest David’s tower being constructed under the instructions of the Bishop in the late 15th century.</item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="dudley_history">
        <item>Dudley castle was originally a wooden motte and bailey castle built shortly after the Norman invasion of 1066.</item>
        <item>The castle was destroyed in 1173 under the orders of Henry II, as its owner had joined a rebellion against him. The castle was rebuilt in the mid 13th century by the Somery family.</item>
        <item>Hugh Despenser, a favourite of Edward II, briefly owned the castle before Edward’s forceful removal from power lead to the castle being take from Despenser.</item>
        <item>The Royalists held the castle during the English Civil War, but the Parliamentarians successfully took the castle in 1646 after a long siege. Parliament purposefully damaged the castle to stop it being used in future conflicts.</item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="tintagel_history">
        <item>Artefacts found on this site suggest it was likely occupied in the Romano-British period.</item>
        <item>In the early middle ages it was likely one of the residences of the regional king of Dummonia.</item>
        <item>The Earl of Cornwall built a castle on this site in the 13th century, although the castle later fell into ruin.</item>
        <item>The castle has a long association with the legend of King Arthur. Legend has evolved to suggest Arthur was born at the castle, although this is nowhere in the works of Geoffrey of Monmouth, who made the Arthurian legend famous in the 12th century.</item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="hylton_history">
        <item>The first castle was likely wooden, and was built shortly after the Norman invasion by the Hylton family, who were rewarded for their support of William the Conqueror with land on the River Wear.</item>
        <item>The castle was later rebuilt as a fortified manor house in the early 15th century. </item>
        <item>The castle stayed in the Hylton family until the last Hylton died without any male heirs in 1746, whereby the castle passed to a nephew called Richard Musgrave.</item>
        <item>The castle went into a period of decay prior to 1812, when it was bought and refurbished by a local businessman. The castle had several other owners in more recent years, with many of them carrying out refurbishment on the castle.</item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="brancepeth_history">
        <item>The original Norman castle built on the site by the Bulmers was rebuilt by the powerful Neville family in the late 14th century.</item>
        <item>The castle was confiscated from the Neville family after they joined a catholic rising against Queen Elizabeth in 1569.</item>
        <item>The current castle generally results from reconstruction of the castle in the 19th century by the Russel family.</item>
        <item>The castle was used as a field hospital during the 1st world war, and was the headquarters for the Durham Light Infantry during the second world war.</item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="mitford_history">
        <item>Before the Norman conquest, the castle was owned by the Mitford family. The daughter, and heir, of the family was married to a Norman knight, called Richard Bertram, by William the Conqueror. </item>
        <item>The castle was an earthwork fortress of the Bertram family from the late 11th century, but was soon after made into a stone castle.</item>
        <item>The castle was seized by forces of King John in 1215, during his war with the Northern Barons. The castle was returned to the Bertram family after the death of King John.</item>
        <item>The castle was taken by the Scottish in 1318, and was badly damaged. It never recovered from this conflict. A pill box was constructed nearby during the second world war to protect against German invasion. </item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="lydford_history">
        <item>The first castle was constructed on the site of an Anglo-Saxon burh shortly after the Norman conquest of Britain.</item>
        <item>The current castle was then built in 1195 to be an administrative centre for the Forest of Dartmoor.</item>
        <item>Henry III granted his brother, the Earl of Cornwall, the castle in 1238. He rebuilt the tower of the castle. During the next few hundred years, the castle’s primary role was as an infamous prison.</item>
        <item>The Royalists used the castle as a military prison during the English Civil War. However, by the early 18th century the castle was in ruin and was totally abandoned in 1833.</item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="brougham_history">
        <item>Due to its strategic location, the Roman’s constructed a fort on this site in the 1st century. This castle was originally made of wood, although was soon after rebuilt in stone.</item>
        <item>The area of Penrith was captured by the Scottish before the Norman invasion of England, and was only recaptured by William II to take the area back into the control of the English crown.</item>
        <item>However, the castle was not built on this site until the reign of King John, who wanted the area secured from Scottish incursions.</item>
        <item>King Edward I was hosted at the castle, an important military base during the wars with Scotland, in 1300. In fact, due to its location, almost 100 years later the castle was taken and sacked by the Scottish.</item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="aydon_history">
        <item>The owner of the castle, Robert, fought with Edward I during his wars in Scotland, including at the Battle of Falkirk where the English were defeated by William Wallace. Around this time, the castle was being constructed into a stone building.</item>
        <item>Aydon was sacked by the Scottish under Robert the Bruce in 1311-1312. But the castle was never taken.</item>
        <item>The owner of the castle, Robery de Raymes, was captured in the Battle of Bannockburn and ransomed for a fee that crippled Robert monetarily. The castle was taken by the Scots in 1315, and was damaged considerably. </item>
        <item>By the 17th century the castle was being used as a farmhouse, and the de Raymes family had long been forced to sell the property as their fortunes waned. </item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="helmsley_history">
        <item>The castle was the main residence of Walter Espect, who was an important supporter of King Stephen during his conflict with the Empress Matilda.</item>
        <item>The de Roos family later owned the castle, although Thomas de Roos was executed by the Yorkists after the Lancastrians were defeated at the Battle of Hexham. The castle was then taken into royal ownership.</item>
        <item>The castle was returned to its original owners on the taking of the crown by the Tudor dynasty, and was upgraded during Tudor times.</item>
        <item>After the Royalist defeat at Marston Moor, the castle was starved into surrender by Parliamentary forces. The castle, like many in England, was then slighted to prevent its future military use.</item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="skipton_history">
        <item>The castle was created by the Normans shortly after William’s “Harrying of the North” to crack down on dissent against his rule. It occupies a key route through the Pennines.</item>
        <item>The castle was frequently involved in the Anglo-Scottish wars during the reigns of Edward I and Edward II. Edward II granted the castle to Piers Gaveson early in his rule. Upon Gaveson’s death the castle passed into the Clifford family.</item>
        <item>The Clifford family were supporters of the Lancastrian cause during the Wars of the Roses. Many of the Clifford’s died fighting during these wars. The Yorkist King Edward took the castle from the Clifford’s although they were reinstated by Henry VII.</item>
        <item>The castle was garrisoned by Royalist’s prior to the English Civil War, and held out for many years before finally surrendering to Parliament in December 1645. The castle was slighted by Parliament following the end of the war.</item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="scarborough_history">
        <item>Due to its strong defensive position, the late Roman empire built a watchtower with a defensive wall on the site.</item>
        <item>Henry II started to construct a fortress on the site in 1159, and the castle was upgraded significantly by King John and Henry III in the early 13th century.</item>
        <item>Piers Gaveston, a favourite of Edward II was captured at Scarborough before his execution by the Earl of Warwick.</item>
        <item>During the Civil War the castle was garrisoned by Parliament, but the garrison leader soon defected to the Royalist cause. The importance of the port to both sides soon lead to a parliamentarian attack on the town and the castle, with it eventually being taken in 1645.</item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="pickering_history">
        <item>Pickering castle was built by William the Conqueror as part of a network of castles to secure the north after the “Harrying of the North” in 1069/70.</item>
        <item>The original wooden structure was replaced with stone by Henry II. He also added a major tower called the Coleman Tower. The castle was further extended by Henry III to secure the North after the First Barons’ War.</item>
        <item>The castle was in the possession of the Earl of Lancaster by the time of the reign of Edward II. The Earl was partially responsible for the downfall of Piers Gaveston, the favourite of Edward. He later entered a rebellion against Edward II in 1321, but was defeated and executed for treason with Edward seizing his lands.</item>
        <item>The Earldom of Lancaster was returned the castle after the accession of Edward III. However, the castle was in a state of decline by the 15th century and took no active role in the Wars of the Roses, despite its association with the House of Lancaster.</item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="bolton_history">
        <item>The castle was originally constructed in the late 14th century by the Scrope family, with the castle intended to be primarily a residence.</item>
        <item>The family was persecuted, with the head of the family being executed by Henry IV, as they had links to Richard II (they were in his court). The family further suffered when it backed the Percy rebellion against Henry, and the result was Henry executed the new head of the family too.</item>
        <item>The Scrope family later supported a rebellion against Henry VIII’s church reforms, and tried to hide one of the leaders of the rebellion, the Abbot of Jervaulx, at Bolton castle. However, the Abbot was later captured and executed by the King’s men.</item>
        <item>Mary Queen of Scots was held as a prisoner at Bolton castle for around 6 months in 1568.</item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="tynemouth_history">
        <item>The castle structure is combined with the ruins of the Benedictine priory where early kings of Northumbria were buried.</item>
        <item>The priory was founded in the early 7th century, and St Oswin, the King of Deira, was buried here after his murder by the ruler of Bernicia. </item>
        <item>The priory was plundered by the Danes at the turn of the 8th century, and it was this raid which lead to increased defences at the priory. The castle held out against the Danes 30 years later, although in 865, 870 and 875 the Church and Monastery were plundered by the Danes.</item>
        <item>Malcolm III of Scotland invaded England in 1093, but was killed at Alnwick by the Earl of Northumberland. Malcolm was buried at the priory before his body was later moved back to Scotland.</item>
    </string-array>
</resources>
