<resources>
    <string name="app_name">CastleAppNF</string>
    <!--History strings-->
    <string name="warkworth_History">\u25CF Warkworth castle was built in the mid-twelfth century originally as a timber castle. \n\n\u25CF In the early 14th century the castle was upgraded by Edward II to protect against Scottish invasion. The castle successfully resisted Scottish invasion during the wars with Scotland. \n\n\u25CFThe Percy family took control of the caslte in 1345 and controlled it for the rest of its active life.</string>
    <string name="dunstan_History">Dunstanburgh Castle was built in the early 14th-century by Thomas of Lancaster, who was the leader of a rebellion against Edward II. The rebellion was ill-fated, and Thomas was captured in battle and executed for his treason. \n\nThe Duchy of Lancaster later took over the castle, with John of Gaunt expanding it greatly. The castle played a significant role in the War of the Roses and was captured and re-captured many times by Lancaster and Yorkish forces. \n\nThe castle took such damage during this sustained war of the roses, and was never fully repaired.</string>
    <string name="rising_History">Built during the age of Norman kings, this Caslte was sold to Queen Isabella who was the widow of Edward II. \n\nIsabella was of French nobility, and after the breakdown of her marriage with the King, she played a role in his removal from power when she allied with Roger Mortimer. \n\nIsabella and Mortimer ruled England for a short peroid after the removal of Edward II, but her son forced control of the country from here in 1330. Isabella was retired to Castle Rising to live out the rest of her days.</string>
    <string name="berk_History">A Norman motte-and-bailey castle built in Norman times, this castle was expanded in the 12th century by Thomas Becket. \n\nThe castle was besieged by King John during the rebellion of the Barons, with the Barons capturing the castle after a siege. \n\nBy the 14th century the castle was used to hold royal prisoners and threats to the crown. </string>
    <string name="warwick_History">Originally a woodern fort constructed by William the Conqueror, this castle was upgraded to Stone in the 12th Century. \n\nThe castle was used as a military fortress until the 17th century, when it was converted by the Greville family into a country home. \n\nThe castle is still in fantastic condition today, and is one of the premier castles in England. Its journey from important military fortress to country home has been seemless.</string>
    <string name="banbury_History">This castle was the site of an important fortress in Northern England as far back at 420 AD. It later became an important Anglo-Saxon stronghold before being destroyed by the vikings in 993. \n\nThe Normans built a new castle on this site, and it has been an important royal castle for much of its history. \n\nIn the war of the roses, it became the first English caslte to be defeated by artillery in a long siege conducted by the Yorkist faction.</string>
    <string name="alnwick_History">Alnwick Castle was built in early Norman times and was a very strong fortress in the north of England. \n\nSitting close to the Scottish border, the castle was captured by King David of Scotland in 1136. It was unsuccesfully sieged by Scottish kings several other times in the century. \n\nIn the 13th century the castle moved into the Percy family, an influentially and powerful historical family in the north of England. In 1572, Thomas Percy was executed for his continued loyalty to the Catholic Church. Another Percy took over the castle following this, but he was also killed for his role in the catholic gunpowder plot. After this the caslte left the family forever.</string>
    <string name="dover_History">Dover Castle is one of the largest castles in England and due to its key location, it is probably the most militarily important castle in the country. \n\nDue to its critical location, a fortification likely existed on this site before the Roman conquest of Britain. It was significantly invested in by many kings, including Henry II who really started to turn the castle into what we can see today. \n\nDuring the English Civil war the castle was taken by the Parliamentarians without a single shot being fired due to its light defences. The castle was a useful and active military during the Napoleonic wars, and so was rebuilt during this peroid. It was also used during the Second World War.</string>
    <string name="raby_History">Raby Castle was built by the influential Neville family in the 14th century, with Cecily Neville, the mother of Yorkist kings Richard and Edward, being born here.  \n\nThe crown took control of the castle when Charles Neville joined forces with Mary, Queen of Scots, to try and put her onto the English throne. \n\nThe castle is now a lived-in country home that is in good condition.</string>
    <string name="caen_History">Caernarfon Castle was a Motte-and-bailey castle built during Norman times. However, when Edward I established English rule over Wales, it was the site of one of the many castles he built in the country. \n\nThe castle was the centre of English rule in Northern Wales. The castle was sacked during a Welsh revolt in the late 13th century, but Welsh rule over the castle only lasted until the next year when the English recaptured it. \n\nDue to their welsh roots, the Tudor dynasty in England saw a reduction in tension between England and Wales, making the castle less important as a military base. To this day, the Prince of Wales is traditionally annointed at this castle.</string>
    <string name="leeds_history">\u25CF Site of a castle since the early 12th century \n\n\u25CF It was a favourite residence of Edward I, who acquired the castle in the 13th century \n\n\u25CF Catherine of Aragorn lived here when married to Henry VIII \n\n\u25CF Used as an arsenal and prison by parliament in the civil war</string>
    <string name="bodiam_history"></string>
    <string name="conway_history"></string>
    <string name="carlisle_history"></string>
    <string name="rochester_history"></string>
    <string name="edinburgh_history"></string>
    <string name="stirling_history"></string>
    <string name="durham_history"></string>
    <string name="conisbrough_history"></string>
    <string name="lancaster_history"></string>
    <string name="york_history"></string>
    <string name="cardiff_history"></string>
    <string name="pontefract_history"></string>
    <string name="richmond_hisotry"></string>
    <string name="prudhoe_history"></string>
    <!--Titles for Details Activity-->
    <string name="opening_times_title">Opening times:</string>
    <string name="operated_by_title">Operated by:</string>
    <string name="status_details_title">Current status:</string>
    <string name="address_title">See location on a map</string>
    <string name="history_title">Brief history of the site</string>
    <string name="audio_title">Detailed history of the site</string>
    <string name="details_rating_title">Site rating</string>

    <string-array name="distance_array">
        <item>Km</item>
        <item>Miles</item>


    </string-array>

    <string-array name="sort_array">
        <item>A-Z</item>
        <item>Distance</item>
        <item>Rating</item>


    </string-array>

    <string-array name="wark_history">
        <item>Built in the mid-twelfth centuryBuilt in the mid-twelfth century</item>
        <item>In 1327, the castle twice held out against Scottish sieges</item>
        <item>The powerful and influential Percy family was given the castle by the crown in the early 14th century</item>
        <item>The Percy family helped Henry IV win the throne from Richard II. But the family later rebelled against the new king. The rebellion was defeated at the battle of Shewsbury.</item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="dunstan_history">
        <item>Built by the Earl Thomas of Lancaster in the early 14th century</item>
        <item>Earl Thomas led an unsuccessful rebellion against King Edward II, causing him to be executed by the king. As a result, the castle was seized by the crown.</item>
        <item>John of Gaunt, who founded the royal House of Lancaster which later took part in the Wars of the Roses, greatly expanded the castle in the late 14th century.</item>
        <item>The castle was traded back and forth during the Wars of the Roses, which represented its strategic importance in the north of England. The damage sustained during these wars was never fully repaired. </item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="rising_history">
        <item>Built during the mid 12th century by an Anglo-Norman lord</item>
        <item>The castle was famously the home of Queen Isabella after the accession of her son, Edward III, to power.</item>
        <item>Queen Isabella joined forces with Roger Mortimer to rebel and bring down her husband Edward II. She ruled along with Mortimer for a short period before her son, Edward III, seized control of the nation.</item>
        <item>The castle quickly became valued for its hunting facilities rather than its strategic importance.</item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="berk_history">
        <item>Built on a key route between London and the Midlands by the Normans in the 11th century</item>
        <item>Thomas Becket was granted the castle in the 12th century, before falling out with the King and being stripped of the castle.</item>
        <item>The castle was besieged by the French Prince Louis in 1216. He was attempting to take control of the crown after the death of King John.</item>
        <item>The castle was taken apart for stone as early as the mid 16th century, and is now a sparse ruin.</item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="warwick_history">
        <item>The castle was originally a wooden fort construction by William I</item>
        <item>The Beauchamp family controlled the castle for much of the medieval period and were influential on the course of English history.</item>
        <item>The castle passed to Richard Neville after the Beauchamp line ended. He was known as the kingmaker for he often held the balance of power during the Wars of the Roses, and was therefore able to gather much power to himself.</item>
        <item>The castle was used as a military base up until the early 17th century, when it was converted into a country house.</item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="bamburgh_history">
        <item>The site was formally a stronghold of Celtic Britons and Anglo-Saxons.</item>
        <item>The fort was destroyed by the Vikings only around 70 years before the arrival of the Normans in England.</item>
        <item>The Normans later constructed a new castle on this site, which has evolved into what can be seen today. </item>
        <item>The castle was the first in England to be defeated by artillery during a siege in the Wars of the Roses. </item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="alnwick_history">
        <item>Alnwick Castle was first built by Norman lords following William the Conqueror’s invasion of England.</item>
        <item>The castle was sieged many times by the Scottish throughout the 12th century, with David I of Scotland successfully capturing it in 1136.</item>
        <item>The powerful and influential Percy family took control of the castle in the 13th century, who turned the castle into a major fortress in the England-Scotland border region.</item>
        <item>The castle was used as a stand-in for Hogwarts during the Harry Potter films</item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="dover_history">
        <item>This version of Dover castle was built in the 11th century.</item>
        <item>However, due to its strategic importance, fortifications on this site likely pre-date the Roman invasions.</item>
        <item>The castle was rebuilt significantly during the Napoleonic wars, and was occupied by British forces to defeat against a potential French Calais-Dover invasion.</item>
        <item>Dover castle was a military command centre during the second world war. The evacuation of Dunkirk was directed from this site.</item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="raby_history">
        <item>Built by the Neville family in the late 14th century</item>
        <item>Cecily Neville was born In the castle, her children included King Edward IV and Richard III, the Yorkist kings of England.</item>
        <item>The Neville family attempted to support the claim of the catholic Mary, Queen of Scots, to the English throne. Following this, the castle was taken into royal ownership.</item>
        <item>The castle is still lived in today.</item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="caen_history">
        <item>The first stone building was built by Edward I of England following his attempts to control Wales.</item>
        <item>The castle was sacked in 1294 during a Welsh rebellion against English rule.</item>
        <item>With the accession of the Tudor family to the crown in 1485 and due to their Welsh heritage, relations between Wales and England improved so the castle was no longer an important military base.</item>
        <item>Despite its poor condition, the royalist controlled castle was sieged several times during the English civil wars.</item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="carlisle_history">
        <item>This castle was built in Norman times and sits close to the ruins of Hadrian’s wall.</item>
        <item>During Roman times, a fort was built on this same site.</item>
        <item>The castle was captured by David, King of Scotland, in the early 12th century. Due to its strategic location on the Anglo-Scottish border it was sieged many times in the middle ages.</item>
        <item>The castle was the site of a bloody siege during the Wars of the Roses, with the Lancastrians teaming up with the Scots to seize the castle from the Yorkists.</item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="conway_history">
        <item>Built by Edward I in the late 13th century, it was one of many castles built in the North of Wales during this time.</item>
        <item>It repelled many welsh sieges, including in 1294 when Madog ap Llywelyn failed to take the castle.</item>
        <item>Richard II took refuge at the castle in 1399, as his power slipped away following defeat by the future King Henry IV. </item>
        <item>The castle was dismantled significantly following the English civil wars as Parliament did not want it used in further revolts.</item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="bodiam_history">
        <item>Built by one of Edward III’s knights in the late 14th century, it is unusual in that is has no keep.</item>
        <item>It was originally constructed to provide protection against the French during the 100 years war.</item>
        <item>The castle’s owner was a supporter of the House of Lancaster during the Wars of the Roses. However, it was taken by Yorkist forces during the wars and only returned to its owner when Henry VII took the crown, effectively ending the Wars of the Roses.</item>
        <item>The castle was dismantled in the 17th century, but in the 19th century began a gradual restoration to its current state.</item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="rochester_history">
        <item>This castle was founded just after the Norman conquest of Britain.</item>
        <item>The castle was sieged by King John in 1215. He managed to bring down a corner of the keep and was later able to starve the defenders into surrender.</item>
        <item>Following repair, the castle was again sieged in 1264 by Simon de Montfort, who was rebelling against the king. Their siege was unsuccessful as royal reinforcements forced off the attackers. However, the castle surrendered when the rebels crushed the king’s forces on the battlefield.</item>
        <item>The castle never fully recovered from these two sieges, and gradually fell into a state of disrepair. </item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="stirling_history">
        <item>The castle is built on a large volcanic rock above the river Forth, and is on a very strategically important site.</item>
        <item>Stirling castle was the site of much fighting during the Wars of Scottish independence, involving characters such as William Wallace, Robert the Bruce, Edward I and Edward II.</item>
        <item>During these wars the battles of Stirling Bridge and Bannockburn took place. These were two of the greatest victories for the Scottish over the English.</item>
        <item>James II infamously murdered Earl Douglas at Stirling castle.  </item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="edin_history">
        <item>Built on a commanding rock, this site has been an important strategic location since at least Roman times.</item>
        <item>This castle is the most besieged castle in Britain, due to its important strategic location and the constant fighting between the English and Scottish throughout the middle ages.</item>
        <item>The castle formerly housed the Scottish royal treasury as it was seen as the safest place in the country to hold such valuable artifacts.</item>
        <item>Bonnie Price Charlie was the last person to try and take the castle. He was unsuccessful, eventually giving up and marching into England to press his claim to the throne. </item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="durham_history">
        <item>The castle was first built in 1072 by William the Conqueror.</item>
        <item>The castle was besieged during one of the many northern rebellions against Norman rule in 1080. </item>
        <item>The castle was put into the hands of Prince-Bishop’s for much of its early medieval history. The role of these bishops was to act as a buffer between England and Scotland. </item>
        <item>The Bishop of Durham still maintains offices at the castle.</item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="conis_history">
        <item>The estates of Conisbrough were in the hands of King Harold prior to his defeat by the Norman king William the Conqueror.</item>
        <item>The Normans originally built a wooden castle here, but it was upgraded to stone in the late 12th century by Hamelin Plantagenet, the illegitamte half-brother of King Henry II.</item>
        <item>Thomas, Early of Lancaster, controlled the castle in 1322 when he rebelled against King Edward II. He was defeated and executed, and the castle was seized personally by King Edward.</item>
        <item>During the Wars of the Roses, the castle was the personal property of Richard of York, and later of his son King Edward Iv. </item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="lancaster_history">
        <item>The castle is part of the Duchy of Lancaster, which is owned by the Monarch of the UK.</item>
        <item>The caslte was damaged by Scottish invasions in 1322 and 1389.</item>
        <item>The parliamentarians captured the castle early in the English Civil War. In response, the king sent an army to retake the city of Lancaster, including the castle. They were unsuccessful and the castle and city remained under parliament control.</item>

    </string-array>

    <string-array name="york_history">
        <item>Clifford's tower was originally a wooden castle built on the orders of William the Conqueror.</item>
        <item>In 1069, the castle was captured an partially destroyed by an anglo-saxon and viking alliance rebelling against William I. The events at York led to the "Harrowing of the North" by William.</item>
        <item>The castle was upgraded to stone in the middle of the 13th century by Henry III.</item>
        <item>The caslte was an important military base during the Anglo-Scottish wars from 1298 to 1338.</item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="cardiff_history">
        <item>The original Motte and Bailey castle was built on this site shortly after the Norman invasion of England.</item>
        <item>The castle was rebuilt in stone in the 12th century.</item>
        <item>The welsh prince Owain Glyndwr took the castle in 1404 during his rebellion against English control of Wales.</item>

    </string-array>

    <string-array name="pontefract_history">
        <item>The castle was originally constructed by the Normans shortly after their conquest of England.</item>
        <item>Thomas, Earl of Lancaster, was executed outside of the walls of the castle following his failed rebellion against King Edward II. Edward was dining in the great hall as the execution was carried out.</item>
        <item>The castle was part of the house of Lancaster, and was seized by Richard II when he banished Henry Bolingbroke. Henry later returned, overthrew Richard and became Henry IV.</item>
        <item>Richard II was held at the castle, and was likely starved to death whilst at the castle.</item>
    </string-array>



    <string name="appwidget_text">EXAMPLE</string>
    <string name="add_widget">Add widget</string>
</resources>
